<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the King, Aug. 14, 1666 being the day of thanksgiving for the late victory at sea / by J. Dolben ...</title>
            <author>Dolben, John, 1625-1686.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1666</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36272</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1833</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15031</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12542660</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12542660</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62993</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36272)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62993)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 313:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the King, Aug. 14, 1666 being the day of thanksgiving for the late victory at sea / by J. Dolben ...</title>
                  <author>Dolben, John, 1625-1686.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>XXXII p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Timothy Garthwait,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1666.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Illustrated t.p.</note>
                  <note>"Printed by His Majesties especial command"</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Anglo-Dutch War, 1664-1667 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62993:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62993:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED BEFORE THE KING, <hi>Aug.</hi> 14. 1666. Being the Day of Thankſgiving for the late VICTORY at Sea.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> J. Dolben, <hi>D. D.</hi> DEAN of <hi>WESTMINSTER,</hi> and Clerk of the Cloſet.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed by His</hi> MAJESTIES <hi>eſpecial Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>woodcut of a ship</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Timothy Garthwait,</hi> 1666.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:62993:2"/>
            <pb n="III" facs="tcp:62993:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Pſal. 18. Ver. 1, 2, 3.</bibl>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>I will love thee, O Lord my ſtrength.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>The Lord is my</hi> Rock, <hi>and my</hi> For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſs, <hi>and my</hi> Deliverer, <hi>my</hi> God, <hi>my</hi> ſtrength, <hi>in whom I will</hi> truſt; <hi>my</hi> Buckler, <hi>the Horn of my</hi> Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, <hi>and my high</hi> Tower.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>I will call upon the Lord, who is worthy to be</hi> Praiſed, <hi>ſo ſhall I be</hi> ſaved <hi>from mine</hi> Enemies.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>AMong the Laws of the <hi>Roman</hi> Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs, as ſome were very Bloudy and Barbarous, ſo others were wiſe and worthy our Imitation. In all thoſe oſtenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of their Glory, there was ever a mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Religion, ſuch as it was; a ceremonious and pompous application to their imaginary
<pb n="IV" facs="tcp:62993:3"/>Deities,<note place="margin">Livius Paſſi n.</note> 
               <hi>Ut ob res bene geſtas Diis immortalibus honos habeatur ſibique Triumphanti urbem invehi liceat,</hi> was the form of their Petition who ſued for that honour. <hi>Idolatry</hi> (the great Mother of <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſme</hi>) was not able to extirpate the natural Conviction which every one hath in himſelf of an Almighty Power governing the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe. But it kept a room; even in thoſe mens Breaſts who were ſo full of themſelves, that they expected to be adored by the reſt of Mankind. That Triumphant <hi>Dictator,</hi> who lorded it over the Lords of the world, before whoſe Axes <hi>Conſuls</hi> and <hi>Pretors</hi> trembled, while he trod proudly on the necks of Captive Kings, and dragg'd them chained like ſlaves after his Chariot, would at the ſame time fall down before a Captive Stock or Stone; <hi>lower</hi> his <hi>Rods</hi> and <hi>Lawrels;</hi> Proſtrating himſelf with all the Enſigns of his Power and Honour, to a rotten deformed <hi>Idol</hi> which he had brought home in a Cart. This was another Triumph in and over their Triumphs, a victory of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion over Infidelity in its greateſt ſtrength and exaltation; for though the Devil did ſo far debauch the underſtandings of reaſonable Creatures, as to make them worſhip him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of God; yet while ſome worſhip was practiſed, and they choſe rather to adore a ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous abominable Deity then none; Even
<pb n="V" facs="tcp:62993:3"/>by theſe Prophane ſacrilegious Rites, the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of a <hi>God</hi> was kept alive and warm in the minds of men; for a <hi>Handle</hi> whereby <hi>in ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of time,</hi> Chriſt and his holy Doctrine took hold on a loſt World, and pull'd them back to the ſervice of the True God. Another thing I obſerve which will be more to our preſent purpoſe; They admitted not a <hi>General</hi> to tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph, unleſs he had finiſhed the deſign upon which he was imployed,<note place="margin">Perduellibus victis, Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctâ Provinciâ.</note> and ſo broken the enemy that he might bring his army home with him, leaving the <hi>Province</hi> quiet to his Succeſſor. But upon any conſiderable ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs they would make ſolemn and publick <hi>ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications</hi> to all their Gods and Goddeſſes, in the name of their abſent Commander, that he might by their favour perfect the Conqueſt which he had already happily began or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced. This is <hi>our</hi> caſe. We are not yet rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for a <hi>Triumph,</hi> but have matter enough for Supplications and Thankſgivings. Our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies are not ſubdued, but by Gods help they are in good meaſure broken and defeated; Our Noble <hi>Conſuls</hi> are not yet ſailing homeward with Lawrels on their <hi>ſtems,</hi> but they are very conveniently <hi>poſted</hi> on the Enemies Coaſt, as Pregnant inſtances to <hi>them</hi> of one <hi>victory</hi> already obtained, and hopeful <hi>Pledges</hi> to <hi>us</hi> of another to follow. And therefore although our joy
<pb n="VI" facs="tcp:62993:4"/>be bounded and circumſcribed, to keep us modeſt, and ſober, and humble; yet have we not onely ground ſufficient, but many high obligations that our Thankſgivings be hearty, and zealous, and univerſal; full of Devotion and ſenſe of our Duty to God; expreſſed by ardent Love to his Goodneſs, Truſt and affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in his Mercy, worſhipping his Majeſty by conſtant Prayers and Praiſes: the onely means to bleſs and conſecrate our paſt ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes, and to procure his aſſiſtance in our fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture undertakings. All which (that I may not ſeem to teach a Chriſtian Congregation onely by <hi>Heathen</hi> examples) you will find re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended to your imitation in the Practice of <hi>David</hi> upon a like occaſion. So the Title en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms us, both here, and 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.</p>
            <p>The Text look two ways, <hi>Backward</hi> upon all the Mercies and Deliverances which God had beſtowed upon <hi>David,</hi> which he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth in the many glorious Titles aſcribed to God, in the firſt and ſecond Verſe, My <hi>Strength,</hi> my <hi>Rock,</hi> and my <hi>Fortreſs,</hi> and my <hi>Deliverer;</hi> my <hi>God,</hi> my <hi>Buckler,</hi> and the <hi>Horn</hi> of my Salvation, and my High <hi>Tower.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Forward,</hi> in the returns of Duty, to which he engageth himſelf: Of <hi>Love,</hi> verſ. 1. <hi>Truſt,</hi> verſ. 2. <hi>Praiſe</hi> and <hi>Prayer,</hi> verſ. 3. Upon all which he] grounds to himſelf a firm Hope
<pb n="VII" facs="tcp:62993:4"/>of being ſaved from his Enemies; <hi>So ſhall I be ſaved from mine Enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I begin with <hi>Davids</hi> acknowledgment of Gods mercies, expreſſed in the Titles of <hi>Strength, Rock, Fortreſs, &amp;c.</hi> Of all theſe words I ſhall not need to ſpeak Particularly, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but ſo many <hi>Synonymous</hi> Phraſes, ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one and the ſame thing, That God had often with great Demonſtrations of his Power and favour ſuccour'd, and ſaved <hi>David.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Greek Tranſlaters have choſen rather to deliver the mind and intention of the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt in plain words, then to render literally the metaphors of the original. Yet muſt we not take this meerly for the exuberance of a <hi>Poetical</hi> ſtyle, much leſs can we imagine <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> to be guilty of that <hi>Battology,</hi> and thoſe <hi>vain repetitions</hi> in his Devotions which our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour condemns in the <hi>Heathens,</hi> Matth. 6.7. It was their practice to worſhip Vanity with Vanity, heaping in their Prayers a multitude of empty inſignificant names upon their vain and more inſignificant Deities. But this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aggeration in <hi>Davids Hymn</hi> flows from the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of a devout and grateful heart, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring to empty and diſcharge its fulneſs, ſtrugling with <hi>Human</hi> infirmity the narrowneſs of our Conceptions, and the poverty and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renneſs
<pb n="VIII" facs="tcp:62993:5"/>of Speech, and endeavouring by any means to intimate, if not expreſs thoſe tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports and extaſies which poſſeſſed his ſoul up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the contemplation of Gods Majeſty and Goodneſs. Beſides (as the <hi>Title</hi> both here, and 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22 directed to obſerve before) this <hi>Hymn</hi> was made in commemoration of all the great things God had done for <hi>David,</hi> and ſo <hi>many</hi> various mercies could not be compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended under any <hi>one</hi> Notion: His <hi>dangers</hi> and diſtreſſes had been ſo numerous, and both in their kind and circumſtance ſo <hi>different,</hi> and <hi>Gods</hi> ways of <hi>vindicating</hi> his ſervant ſo <hi>unlike</hi> one another; ſometimes by <hi>warning</hi> him of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous deſigns, that he might avoid or coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwork them; ſometimes by <hi>defeating</hi> dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Councels, and turning pernicious wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to folly; By <hi>diverting</hi> his Enemies, By defending him againſt their force, or by ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling him to <hi>overcome</hi> it. And as ſo many and ſo different things could not be put together in one <hi>ſtanza</hi> of a <hi>Pſalm,</hi> otherwiſe then in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral terms, ſo <hi>David</hi> could not ſatisfie himſelf but by crowding in all the general words and <hi>Appellatives</hi> which plain or figurative ſpeech afforded,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Theodoret. in Locum.</note> accompanying doubtleſs every ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral word with a proper diſtinct act of Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a new heat and flame of love and zeal; ſo that all together (like the <hi>Milky way</hi>) they
<pb n="IX" facs="tcp:62993:5"/>ſeem one Celeſtial fire, but are many.</p>
            <p>That we may ſee how well ſuch a full acknowledgment would become us, how well all theſe Names and Titles attributed by <hi>David</hi> to God would ſound in our mouths, if we would aſcribe them with <hi>Davids</hi> Devotion and Affection; Give me leave to look back, not ſo far as he does, to the <hi>whole life</hi> of a Man, but to that new <hi>Epocha</hi> of our lives, the new Birth and <hi>Reſtauration</hi> of all things to us. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks that ſhould be remembred every <hi>Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving-day,</hi> without which we ſhould never have had any Thankſgiving day at all. Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der then in what condition we were this time <hi>ſeven years,</hi> when the laſt <hi>Effort</hi> we could make, or Project for the recovery of our Country, was miſerably defeated; Shall I ſay by the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery of ſome, the folly and cowardize of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, or rather by the good Providence of God? who deſigned to ſhew us the vanity of all our contrivances, and the impoſſibility of our being ſaved by any other means, then the miraculous interpoſition of his help, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by make us humble enough for ſuch a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance. You cannot but remember, That we did not then draw our Breath, otherwiſe then <hi>Precariouſly,</hi> and at the mercy of impotent <hi>Fanatical,</hi> and now enraged Tyrants, from whoſe <hi>Principles,</hi> as well as malice, nothing
<pb n="X" facs="tcp:62993:6"/>was to be expected but Robberies, Maſſacres and Deſolations; private miſchiefs and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Ruine. Men that could not poſſibly agree to eſtabliſh themſelves, and beſides that they conſpired to undo all but themſelves; their very diſagreement (had they deſigned nothing towards it) muſt neceſſarily have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed the Nation.</p>
            <p>Who would have expected, that through this black Cloud, a comfortable light, and day of Salvation, ſhould dawne and break upon us within a few Months? Who durſt hope, or almoſt Pray, (in ſo deep a deſpair) that out of this horrid <hi>Chaos,</hi> a World of Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Order ſhould ariſe ſo ſoon, and we be ſurpriſed (as in a dream) with a perfect re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcue from all we feared, and a quiet enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of whatſoever we could wiſh? This was clearly the <hi>Work</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and God alone; a meer miracle of Mercy, wrought in deſpight of ſo much actual <hi>force</hi> at home, ſo much <hi>Councel</hi> of all States and Princes abroad, and the yet more dangerous oppoſitions of our own <hi>Provocations,</hi> perverſly and inſolently contending againſt Gods goodneſs, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it far more reaſonable for us to look for a <hi>hand upon the Wall,</hi> writing a viſible inrever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ſentence of extirpation, then ſecretly and powerfully working our deliverance behind
<pb n="XI" facs="tcp:62993:6"/>it. And therefore were there nothing elſe in our caſe, we muſt confeſs that this alone hath filled all the expreſſions of <hi>David</hi> in my Text, and we ſhall think our ſelves bound for ever to celebrate our Good God as our <hi>Refuge and Defence, our Deliverer, the Horn of our Salvation, and our High Tower, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>TO come cloſe and home to our preſent bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs; When the impudent injuſtice of our <hi>Neighbours</hi> made this <hi>War</hi> neceſſary, we ſoon ſaw we ſhould be engaged to contend with the moſt powerful enemies in the World, without the aſſiſtance of any friend; And, perhaps this little world of ours, were it una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous and entire, vigorouſly exerting all its force, might be able to defend it ſelf againſt ſo much of the greater. But we are full of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>price,</hi> and humorous Emulations and <hi>Piques,</hi> which trouble and diſcountenance, and worſe things which hinder and obſtruct Publick En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſes. The infirmities of ſome, and the wickedneſs of others weaken our hands, and make us little more then <hi>half</hi> our ſelves: <hi>One</hi> ſort do no good, and <hi>others</hi> all the harm they can. So deſperately mad are they,<note place="margin">Liv. l. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> that like <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pius</hi> his Legions, they would rather be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by any Enemy, then live to ſee their <hi>Prince</hi> have the honour of ſaving and defending them.</p>
            <pb n="XII" facs="tcp:62993:7"/>
            <p>Theſe things ſhame us, and diſadvantage our Cauſe; but they exalt the Glory of God, and make his help afforded us more conſpicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: For notwithſtanding all this, He gave us the <hi>laſt year</hi> a glorious <hi>Victory,</hi> which brought forth good fruit and great effects. And <hi>this</hi> year he hath not been wanting to us. In the <hi>Firſt</hi> Fight he brought us off without diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, nay, perhaps with more honour (the circumſtances of the Battle conſidered) then a <hi>full</hi> Victory could have challenged, had we been evenly matched. And your Enemies Beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour <hi>then</hi> will teach you how to value the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory you have <hi>now.</hi> Lord! how did they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult and brave it all over <hi>Europe?</hi> How un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able were they to govern themſelves, when they pretended to have maſtered <hi>us?</hi> If <hi>Bonefires</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> Wit, <hi>French</hi> Brags, and ſome <hi>Engliſh</hi> Deſpondence could have conquer'd us, we had been utterly undone. But now behold how the <hi>Scene</hi> is changed; we have ſeen our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors fairly beaten; and they who lately told the World that the <hi>narrow Seas</hi> were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as ſubject to them as their own <hi>Ditches,</hi> and talked, as if like <hi>Xerxes,</hi> they would bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle and fetter the Captive Ocean, are ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully fled like him broken and ſhatter'd through <hi>thoſe</hi> very Seas, and left them to the poſſeſſion of their ancient rightful owners.
<pb n="XIII" facs="tcp:62993:7"/>And now their countenance is alter'd with their fortune: Heretofore they were like the <hi>Grecian Wraſtler,</hi> who being thrown, would ſpring up nimbly from the ground, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently aver, that he had given his adverſary the fall. Now they are more ingenuous and modeſt, but not more quiet; their Rants and Huffs are exerciſed among themſelves: And having by a calm eſcaped an imminent ruine at Sea, they are ſhaken by Tempeſts and Storms at Land; Revilings and accuſations fly like <hi>Broadſides</hi> among their great Captains, and the <hi>wiſe</hi> men cannot make the <hi>valiant</hi> ones agree which of them contributed moſt to their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing beaten. That all this hath been done for us, and in a time while the devouring <hi>Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence</hi> rageth in our bowels, and kills far more at home, then our Enemies can abroad; That the ſpreading Contagion, which hath ſeized all quarters of our Land, hath been reſtrained from hindring our great buſineſs, either in the <hi>Fleet,</hi> the <hi>Court,</hi> or this <hi>City,</hi> is of the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful goodneſs of God, who though he will chaſtiſe, will not deſtroy us, though he take us into his <hi>own</hi> hand to correct us for our a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment, yet ſuffers us not to <hi>fall into the hands of Man,</hi> but both in Judgment and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy approves himſelf our <hi>Strength,</hi> our <hi>Deliverer,</hi> the <hi>horn</hi> of our <hi>Salvation,</hi> and our <hi>high Tower;</hi>
               <pb n="XIV" facs="tcp:62993:8"/>and all this, to try us by one experiment more, whether when we have found him as good to us as he was to <hi>David,</hi> we will be as thankful to him as <hi>David</hi> was; <hi>Love</hi> him, <hi>Truſt</hi> in him, <hi>Praiſe</hi> him, and <hi>Pray</hi> to him.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Love him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVHo can do other then love God, in whom he lives, and moves, and hath his Being? How can we refrain loving that Infinite Wiſdom, and Power, and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which hath made the Univerſe, and wonderfully diſpoſed it in a beautiful Harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and mutual correſpondence, and doth ſo ſweetly govern, and carefully ſuſtain all the parts of it? Beſide <hi>David</hi> knew <hi>Love</hi> to be the ſum of Gods Law, and the <hi>Compendium</hi> of mans Duty to him, and could not be a <hi>Man after Gods own heart</hi> without doing this before, and then what new thing doth he promiſe in my Text? Further, To love God for his Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits onely, is but to love our ſelves, and our own conveniences; to love him as we do fair weather, and ſweet air; as we love meat, drink, and ſleep; And the inſincerity of ſuch a love would be ſure to appear upon the tryal which Satan deſired to put on <hi>Job:</hi>
               <note place="margin">J b 1.9, 10, 11.</note> While <hi>God maketh a hedg about its, and bleſſeth all that we have,</hi>
               <pb n="XV" facs="tcp:62993:8"/>perphas we ſhall love him; But if <hi>he put forth his hand, and take all we have,</hi> our Love being grounded on no other Principle, will go away with our goods, and we ſhall be in danger of <hi>Curſing him to his face.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We are to love God for his own <hi>Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies;</hi> We are to love him becauſe he <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires</hi> it; and the more, Becauſe having a juſt Right and Power to exact from us the moſt painful hard ſervices: He is ſo gracious, as to demand no more, but that we love him; that we be not ſo much his <hi>Servants,</hi>
               <note place="margin">J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hn 15.15.</note> as his <hi>Friends.</hi> This is our ſtanding ordinary Duty; Indeed, this is all we can perform; We can do no more then love God; That is both the Perfection of our Obedience here<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſhall be of our Happineſs in Heaven. But yet this love is capable of degrees; The <hi>affection</hi> may and muſt be at ſometimes, and on ſome occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions more intenſe then at others, and the <hi>acts</hi> more lively and vigorous, when our hearts are impregnated, and our ſervices called forth by ſignal extraordinary demonſtrations as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of Gods love to us. We ought ever to love God with all our <hi>Souls.</hi> that is, <hi>heartily</hi> and <hi>entirely;</hi> yet this hinders not, but that the love which was always <hi>true,</hi> and void of Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, proceeding (as S. <hi>Paul</hi> derives it) out of a <hi>pure heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.5.</note> 
               <hi>and a good conſcience, and faith un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned,</hi>
               <pb n="XVI" facs="tcp:62993:9"/>may now be more ardent then uſual. That the fire which was alive in the <hi>Embers</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, may now burn out, and flame with a <hi>Seraphick</hi> heat and brightneſs, when God hath deſcended thus to ſtir it up, to invite, and court, and even raviſh our affections with the abundance of his favours. This <hi>David</hi> inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates in the very Text; For though we have it onely, I <hi>will love,</hi> yet the Original expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſignifies, I will <hi>ardently</hi> or affectionately love thee: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> out of my <hi>Bowels,</hi> or from the bottom of my heart will I love thee,<note place="margin">Ex intimis vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hus. Tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l.</note> and ſo ſome of the beſt <hi>Tranſlations</hi> render it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">To t'ame<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ò affettu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſa mente. Dio dati.</note>Well then, if this be the Scale and Standard of our Duty in this behalf, that our Love ought to riſe in proportion to the Benefits we receive; As our Saviour indeed ſets it in the <hi>Goſpel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 7.47.</note> where he tells us, that the moſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged perſon <hi>will love moſt;</hi> and were it not ſo, there could be no ſuch ſin as <hi>Ingratitude</hi> in the World; that odious inhumane Crime would loſe all the ground and reaſon both of its guilt and ſhame. Then it will preſently be evident to all men, how much we of <hi>this</hi> Nation ought to love God, who hath ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded in his favours to us. But how much we do love him is hard to ſay; for the expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of our affection are very untoward: L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke the Courſe and rude <hi>Careſſes</hi> of <hi>Ruſsian</hi> Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands
<pb n="XVII" facs="tcp:62993:9"/>to their Wives; our kindneſs looks much more like to <hi>Anger</hi> and ill nature, then Love. If to diſobey, diſhonour, injure, and affront, to do every thing that will diſpleaſe God, and <hi>grieve</hi> his <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> be Love; then we love him extreamly.</p>
            <p>But if there be any Truth, in what Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Senſe, and the Uniform Voice of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind affirm of <hi>Love,</hi> That it is an active vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Principle, working <hi>mightily</hi> in the hearts of Men, Provoking, and even conſtraining them to do every thing which may be agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to thoſe they Love, and accordingly hath produced wonderful, Prodigious effects in Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Friendſhips. If the Holy Scriptures and Hiſtories of Times truly Chriſtian, deceive us not, in repreſenting the ſincere Love of God, as an affection which can neither be <hi>diſſembled,</hi> nor <hi>ſuppreſſed,</hi> being always cheerfully and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defatigably employ'd in his ſervice. If it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voureth <hi>Difficulties,</hi> caſteth out<note n="(a)" place="margin">1 John 4.18.</note> 
               <hi>Fear,</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Pſal. 119. <hi>ſaepe.</hi>
               </note> Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth <hi>Labour</hi> eaſie and deſireable, delighting not onely in the <hi>ſweat</hi> of its Brows, but in the moſt <hi>Bloudy Agonies</hi> and <hi>Conflicts;</hi> breaking through the Briars and Thorns of an accurſed World, and the many flaming ſwords which Satan draws againſt it; making it ſelf a Paradiſe, and Heaven upon Earth, in the doing Gods Will, in walking with, and<note n="(c)" place="margin">1 John 4.15<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 16.</note> 
               <hi>dwelling</hi> in him: For
<pb n="XVIII" facs="tcp:62993:10"/>which reaſon Love is called, The<note n="(d)" place="margin">Rom. 13.10.</note> 
               <hi>fulfilling</hi> of the <note n="e" place="margin">Gal 5 10.</note> 
               <hi>Law;</hi> The keeping God's <note n="(f)" place="margin">1 John 5.3</note> 
               <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments;</hi> That whereon all the Law and the Prophets <note n="(g)" place="margin">Mat. 22 40</note> 
               <hi>depend;</hi> The <note n="(h)" place="margin">1 J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hn 4 7.8</note> 
               <hi>knowing</hi> God, and being <hi>known</hi> of him: The <note n="(i)" place="margin">E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h 3.17.</note> 
               <hi>Root</hi> and <hi>Ground</hi> of Religion, and the choiceſt, moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent <note n="(k)" place="margin">Ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>5.22.</note> 
               <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uit</hi> of the <hi>Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If this be the true Character of that Divine Vertue (as indeed theſe are the Lineaments and Features by which it was moſt eminently diſcernible, in the unparallell'd Example of our dear Lord and Saviour, and in the firſt Copies taken from thence, the Primitive Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs and Confeſſors) Then may ſomething like to it be found in our Fancies, our Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes or Profeſſions, but not the leaſt ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of it appears in our Lives and Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Unhappy Nation that we are! for whom the eſſences of things, and the Defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Duty muſt be quite changed, ere we can pretend to that diſpoſition towards God, which Nature dictates, and the bare apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of a Deity exacts! I am not willing to utter words of ill <hi>Omen</hi> this day; but thus much I cannot refrain from ſaying, That had God expreſſed his kindneſs to us, no otherwiſe then we have done our returns of Love to Him, we had not now been here.</p>
            <pb n="XIX" facs="tcp:62993:10"/>
            <p>Surely <hi>David</hi> lov'd God at another rate; elſe we ſhould not have found him in one Pſalm <hi>panting</hi> and <hi>languiſhing</hi> after him like an em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boſs'd ſpent Dear;<note place="margin">Pſal. 42. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 2.</note> Grieved and afflicted for being kept from his preſence;<note place="margin">Pſal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>20.84<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2.69.9.</note> Languiſhing and fainting, with deſire to get into his Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; burnt up, and devour'd with Zeal for it in others. Not onely his Book of Pſalms, but his whole life could not otherwiſe have been ſo full of jealouſie for God's Honour, Delight in his Commands, and every thing that may expreſs a Will knit and united to that of God (as the <hi>Chaldee</hi> hath it here) which is the true and proper effect of Love.</p>
            <p>Indeed <hi>David</hi> could not without ſuch a love of God, have perform'd well thoſe acts of Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety and Devotion which he promiſeth in my Text; Could not Truſt in him, Praiſe him, or Pray to him acceptably, with hope to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from his Enemies. Nor can we (how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever our Fancies and Dreams of Religion de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive us) and therefore muſt be ſure to take it along with us throughout<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And firſt to help us, and give us ground and foundation for our Truſt in God; the next thing in my Text.</p>
            <p>TRuſt, we know is an act of Friendſhip, and the greateſt fruit it yields, Mutual Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, ſpringing naturally from Mutual Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
<pb n="XX" facs="tcp:62993:11"/>I can ſafely rely upon that Perſon whom I therefore love, becauſe I eſteem him ſo good, that he will not fail any juſt expectation, and whoſe affection to me is my double Pledg that he will ſurely anſwer mine. But if I doubt either of theſe two things, Love and Truſt vaniſh to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; ſo that we muſt both love God, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that he loves us, before we can Truſt in him: For though God's Goodneſs be Infinite, and have wonderfully abounded to us, yet being free in its exerciſe, it will be preſumption and folly, not truſt, to expect any thing further from him but according to the methods of his Wiſdom revealed unto us in his Promiſes, and he hath promiſed his favours onely to thoſe that love him; And if we love him, then ſhall we Truſt in him, both with a <hi>ſteady</hi> and <hi>humble</hi> Confidence: Not murmuring when we want the ſucceſs we expect, nor growing inſolent when we have it. Love will not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer us to ſuſpect his Goodneſs if every event come not up to our wiſhes; Nor cenſure his Wiſdom, though ſometimes we diſcern not the reaſon of his Providence: Much leſs ſhall we juſtle him out of his Throne, and put in for our ſhare in governing the World, ſetting up a Counter-Deity of our own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel and Force. Theſe are generally the two great faults of men in our Condition; Not
<pb n="XXI" facs="tcp:62993:11"/>ſubmitting to the Wiſdom and Goodneſs of God; And relying too much upon the Arm of Fleſh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And have we never been guilty of either of them? Have we never quarrelled and grum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled if there were a ſhip leſs taken then we had predeſtined in our Fancy? Any thing fallen out otherwiſe then we had ſet it down in the Gallery, or the Coffee-houſe? Do we not in the computation of our ſtrength for the War, make falſe Muſters, paſſing our own Force and Courage twice over upon the Rolls, and leaving God quite out? Imagine our ſelves ſufficient Deliverers and Saviours to our ſelves, and forgetting that God is our <hi>Strength, The Rock of our Defence, and the Horn of our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</hi> I fear ſomething of this may have been the Provocation which hath mov'd God to Diſcipline us with his own Sword, the Plague, at home, while he ſaves us from that of the Enemy abroad. Lately to ſhew us dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in an unequal Encounter, and even now to check our Victory, and ſnatch much of its fruit out of our hands when we were juſt graſping it, and ſeem'd to our ſelves almoſt poſſeſs'd of a full and final Conqueſt: And this hath he done, not by animating our droop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Enemies with new Courage, or ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their feeble hands with freſh force and activity; but meerly by withholding the
<pb n="XXII" facs="tcp:62993:12"/>Breath of his Wind, that we may be convinced upon how Particular and conſtant attendance of Providence upon us, our felicity depends; which if it be ſuſpended but for one moment, we preſently falter; if the influence of God's Power and Goodneſs (that ſoul of our affairs) do not exert it ſelf in every inſtance, immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately our nerves are relaxed, and our ſpirits damp'd, and we begin to languiſh without ſtrength or motion. This being duly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, I hope will engage us not onely to Love God more ardently, and Truſt in him more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely and firmly, but doing both, to Praiſe and Pray to him more affectionately, That ſo we may both now and always be ſafe from our Enemies. <hi>I will call upon the Lord, who is worthy to be praiſed; So ſhall I, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I fear there is not ſo much of my time left, as of my Subject; Wherefore I will join theſe two Duties of <hi>Prayer</hi> and <hi>Praiſe</hi> in my Exhortation, as the <hi>Chaldee</hi> and <hi>Greek</hi> do in the Text it ſelf, who read both of them; <hi>Praiſing I will Pray:</hi> And they cannot be more joint and united in any Expreſſion, then they are in their own natures, <hi>Praiſe</hi> being one, and the moſt noble Part of Prayer, that which is moſt peculiarly and eminently the Worſhip of God; For though when we Petition him for the Benefits we deſire; or againſt the Evils
<pb n="XXIII" facs="tcp:62993:12"/>we fear<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> we do tacitly and by conſequence ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg both his Power and his Goodneſs, yet do we more expreſly and directy Honour and Glorifie God, when our ſouls are pour'd out in cheerful Hallelujah's, hearty and joyful celebrations of his holy Name, who is the Lord <hi>Bleſſed for ever. Whoſo offereth me Thanks,</hi> and Praiſe, he<note n="(a)" place="margin">Pſ 50.23.</note> 
               <hi>Honoureth</hi> me, ſaith <hi>David;</hi> and how much <hi>David</hi> thought ſo, appears by this that all his Pſalmes are ſo full of thoſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, as in the Original they are juſtly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>The Book of Praiſes:</hi> And why are not our lives as full of them too? We miſtake our ſelves, if we think this Duty confined to great Feſtivals and ſolemn Thankſgivings, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon our Calendars, or the Kings Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations; Holy <hi>Job,</hi> in the depth of his ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, and the midſt of his great diſtreſſes, when he had at once loſt both his Wealth, and his Children, all the ſupports and comforts of this life, Even upon the Dunghil<note n="(b)" place="margin">Job 1 21.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſeth the Name of the Lord his God, who had both given, and taken away;</hi> To teach us, that we can never be in a condition ſo wretched and uncomforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, wherein we may not find ſomewhat, for which we ought to Praiſe God, and adore and magnifie his goodneſs towards us; not onely although we be afflicted and caſt down, but even becauſe we are ſo.</p>
            <pb n="XXIV" facs="tcp:62993:13"/>
            <p>Would we allow our ſelves ſome time to meditate ſeriouſly on the incomprehenſible Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies of the Divine Nature; To conſider how all God's Attributes have been employed and exerciſed for our Good, To underſtand what it was at firſt to be created out of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and put into a capacity of hapineſs; What need we had of Mercy, and how unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy we were of it, when by a fooliſh Diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience we had obliged and confined our ſelves to endleſs wo; and then at what a rate our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption was procured; That by the Bloud of Chriſt, not onely Pardon, but Eternal Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs was purchaſed for us; Would we recol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect the ſeveral inſtances of God's Care and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence in the preſervation of our lives, and all our worldly concernments; but eſpecially the continual endeavours of his Grace and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit, to conduct us ſafe to the enjoyment of that Bleſſedneſs which his Infinite Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Goodneſs have prepared for us: Such Reflections as theſe (would we ſuffer them to ſettle and fix upon us) muſt needs fill our ſouls with the <hi>Love</hi> of God, and our mouths with his <hi>Praiſes:</hi> This would kindle in us a zealous Concern and Paſſion for the Glory of God, and we ſhould apprehend no happineſs upon Earth, but in the promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his honour among men; Our hearts
<pb n="XXV" facs="tcp:62993:13"/>would be like <hi>Altars</hi> of Incenſe, with a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Heavenly fire burning on them, and ſending up continually our Euchariſtial obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that odour of ſweet ſmell made of holy Oyl and fragrant Spices, Love and Joy in the Lord, and the Cloud of this Incenſe would co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the <hi>Mercy Seat;</hi> The aſſiſtant Angels would (as the <hi>Jews</hi> ſay) go up in this Cloud to offer our Lauds unto God, and bring back from him Grace, and Peace, and Salvation in returns unto us. 'Tis for want of this (becauſe we are ſuch ſtrangers to God and our ſelves) that the life of every Chriſtian is not a continual Euchariſt; That we come ſo ſeldom, and with ſuch coldneſs and Indevotion, to join with the Church Militant in her Sacrifice of Praiſe, the Holy <hi>Communion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hebr. 13 15.</note> that great peculiar inſtance of our Religion, wherein Chriſt hath commanded us to continue a perpetual thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful remembrance of all God's Mercies, and particularly of his Death (which comprehends them all) and there to connect our poor Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to his powerful eternal interceſſions, that ſo both our Petitions and Praiſes may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to God. 'Tis for want of this that the Children of God are ſo unwilling to have their Converſation in Heaven, to join and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate in this Honourable, delectable Duty of Praiſing God with the Church Triumphant,
<pb n="XXVI" facs="tcp:62993:14"/>where Saints and Angels inceſſantly Praiſe God, having nothing to ask or beg of him, but in behalf of us. We deceive our ſelves groſly and dangerouſly, while we think we can be Religious without Praiſing God often, and heartily, and cheerfully, in Private as well as Publick. Alas! our loud and clamorous Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, how many or importunate ſoever they be, ſeparate from this, are but Hypocritical Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, terminated in our own intereſts, not in God, or his Glory: And our Prayers would be as few as our Praiſes, but that the love of the world and our ſelves, which damps the love of God in our hearts, and ſuffers us not to delight and rejoice in Praiſing him; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times prompts us to call on him, to fly to his help in diſtreſs; make us look up (like the <hi>Jews</hi> in the Wilderneſs) when we feel our ſelves <hi>ſtung.</hi> And this ſtrange fire on the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, looks like the True, burns and blazeth for a while, and makes us think our ſelves ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Religious, when alas! we are onely very fore, or very fearful, and our <hi>neceſsities</hi> and <hi>diſtreſſes</hi> are devout, not we. I need not Preſs that fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whereof every one hath a ſufficient con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction in this, that while our caſe is thus, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion comes upon us onely by <hi>catches</hi> and <hi>ſtarts,</hi> and even as in an <hi>Ague,</hi> we have as many <hi>cold Fits as hot.</hi> When the violence of that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſe
<pb n="XXVII" facs="tcp:62993:14"/>pulſe which warm'd us, is ſpent, we freeze a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, when the Calamity or terror which put us into a haſty fermentation is taken off, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately we ſettle upon our lees; VVhen he <hi>kills</hi> us, <hi>then we ſeek him;</hi> we turn early and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire after God, when we remember that <hi>God</hi> is our <hi>ſtrength,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 78.</note> and the moſt High God is our <hi>Redeemer;</hi> but as ſoon as the <hi>Judgment</hi> is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, and we have ſwallowed and <hi>digeſted</hi> the <hi>Mercy,</hi> we turn back and tempt the Holy One of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> VVe think no more of his <hi>Hand,</hi> and of the Day wherein he <hi>delivered us</hi> from <hi>our Enemies:</hi> VVhereas were a habit of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion firmly ſetled in us, rooted and grounded on the love of God, and conſcience of our Duty, it would be both Permanent and Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form in all its exerciſes, VVe ſhould not think to uſe God onely as a Property or Conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, but adore the Majeſty of our Almighty Soveraign Lord, and delight as much to Praiſe him for the Benefits we have received, as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive any new ones from his hand! VVhat then ſhall I ſay? Shall I reproach a Chriſtian Congregation, by exhorting them to love God? I am aſhamed to do that, and I have ſaid enough already, (if any thing be enough) by telling you, that without Loving God, you <hi>ought</hi> not to <hi>Truſt</hi> in him, you cannot <hi>Praiſe</hi> or Pray to him; your Praiſes will be but <hi>Flatteries,</hi> and
<pb n="XXVIII" facs="tcp:62993:15"/>your Prayers <hi>indignities</hi> and <hi>affronts.</hi> Shall I deſire you to be more frequent, and more zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous in your Praiſes? Sure I need not requeſt you (if you mean to go to Heaven) to practice that beforehand here, which muſt there be your onely Employment; to beſeech you not to think that a trouble now, which then will be your Happineſs and Glory: I will rather tell you, that God needs none of all theſe things from you; Your Love does not <hi>benefit,</hi> nor your Praiſes <hi>exalt</hi> him; <hi>He</hi> is the ſame Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent Majeſty, Infinitely happy in Himſelf, whether you depend on his Protection, and beg your daily Bread and all other good things at his hands; or whether neglecting both thoſe Duties, you live as <hi>without God</hi> in the <hi>World:</hi> But <hi>He</hi> is pleaſed, when you <hi>love</hi> and <hi>honour</hi> him, becauſe he is delighted in the obedience of his Creature; and nothing is ſo agreeable to him, as that we ſhould give him thoſe <hi>oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions</hi> to <hi>love us,</hi> and do <hi>us good:</hi> which if you thus qualifie your ſelves to receive his favour, I can aſſure you he will do, as the Prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> here aſſures himſelf. Upon theſe Terms we ſhall be ſafe from our Enemies. <hi>So ſhall I, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>SO <hi>ſhall I be ſafe,</hi> otherwiſe <hi>I ſhall not:</hi> VVe cannot promiſe our ſelves to be ſafe by our own ſtrength, For were it never ſo great, it may
<pb n="XXIX" facs="tcp:62993:15"/>be <hi>matched and exceeded;</hi> And were we never ſo much Maſters of our <hi>Enemies,</hi> we are not Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of <hi>Occaſion;</hi> We may, and have been o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliged to fight upon <hi>diſadvantage;</hi> We are not Commanders of the <hi>Seas,</hi> nor of the <hi>Winds,</hi> which God keeps in his <hi>Treaſure.</hi> Laſt year they were helpful to us, They were otherwiſe this year. And if we cannot protect our ſelves, Who ſhall protect us? I have heard, that one of our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies hath ſaid with <hi>contempt</hi> and <hi>ſcorne</hi> enough, We have no Friend <hi>But God! Does he make ſuch But's?</hi> I pardon his <hi>raillery,</hi> and heartily embrace the good <hi>Omen</hi> of it. If we have no Friend but God, then we have him, and if he be our Friend, I am ſure we need not fear what man can do againſt us. Neither they, we have ſo oft conflicted with, nor they who hover fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther off, expecting an opportunity to fall upon us when we are <hi>ſore,</hi> can be able to do us harm. He is too much a Coward, that dreads any Enemy, when he hath Omnipotence it ſelf to <hi>ſecond</hi> him. But he is more a fool who may have ſuch a <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond</hi> and <hi>Patron,</hi> and yet will be ſo far want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to himſelf, as not to procure his favour and aſſiſtance; Eſpecially, when the terms upon which it is to be had, are ſo eaſie, nay ſo deſire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, that the <hi>Condition</hi> of acquiring it is more valuable then the <hi>thing</hi> it ſelf, it being a far greater happineſs to <hi>love</hi> and <hi>ſerve</hi> God as we ought, then
<pb n="XXX" facs="tcp:62993:16"/>to be ſecured by him from all the harm this world can do.</p>
            <p>For my part, it ſhall ſuffice me that I have brought the buſineſs <hi>home,</hi> and laid it at your own doors. I dare ſay there is no Perſon in this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, who wiſheth not all ſafety to his <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, Honor</hi> to the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Victory</hi> to his <hi>Armes.</hi> You muſt therefore think it an advantage to be directed how your ſelves may have the ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to bear a part in the atchieving all this, which you do (and are ſo much concerned to) wiſh. I will preſently take of that regreat which your gallantry hath raiſed in many of your thoughts, for your being detained by employment, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other circumſtance of your Conditions, from ſhewing your courage, and gaining a ſhare in the honor of the late <hi>Engagements. Courage!</hi> break off your <hi>Sins</hi> by <hi>Repentance,</hi> live a <hi>Chriſtian, devout, holy life and pray earneſtly</hi> for Gods gracious favor and ſuccour, ſo ſhall you ſerve the King as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderably as any <hi>Volontier</hi> in the Fleet. Here is a Project to raiſe an <hi>Army eaſily, ſpeedily,</hi> without <hi>charge</hi> or <hi>trouble,</hi> and ſuch a one as could I ſee formed, I ſhould be ſo much tempted to deſpiſe all our Enemies: No <hi>Age</hi> or <hi>Sex</hi> but are fit to be liſted in it. The impotent <hi>Old man</hi> on his <hi>Couch,</hi> the <hi>Lady</hi> in her <hi>Cloſet,</hi> the <hi>Sick</hi> and <hi>Weak</hi> upon their <hi>Beds,</hi> without <hi>Danger</hi> or <hi>Fatigue</hi> at <hi>Sea,</hi> every one in their own ſtation, where infirmity
<pb n="XXXII" facs="tcp:62993:16"/>or tenderneſs hath ranked them, may fight and be certainly <hi>victorious.</hi> Whoever can but morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie a <hi>Luſt, forſake a Sin;</hi> kindle an ardent <hi>love</hi> to God in his heart, ſhed a <hi>Tear,</hi> ſend up a <hi>Prayer,</hi> a <hi>ſigh or groan</hi> to Heaven; may thereby with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any other Artillery <hi>reach</hi> and <hi>gall</hi> the <hi>Enemy</hi> at what diſtance ſoever. By the ſecret inviſible influence of your Devotion, you may ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then the hearts and hands of your Friends. While your hearts are right with God, and you hold up <hi>pure hands in Prayer</hi> (like <hi>Moſes</hi> in the Mount) theirs will be victorious in Battail. But then remember that though, when <hi>Moſes</hi> his hands were up, <hi>Joſua</hi> prevaild, yet when they were ſet down, <hi>Amalek</hi> prevail'd. Succeſs va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried and ſhifted from the <hi>People</hi> and <hi>Army</hi> and <hi>Cauſe of God,</hi> to the <hi>accurſed Nations</hi> whom he had vowed to <hi>deſtroy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 17.11.</note> upon every <hi>intermiſſion of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes Prayer.</hi> And therefore unleſs we think Gods honour more concerned in our affairs, then in theirs whom he had choſen and promiſed, and avow'd to all the world that he would give them the ſpoils and inheritance of their Enemies. Unleſs we think our adverſaries more accurſed then thoſe whom God had <hi>ſworn</hi> to have <hi>War</hi> with for <hi>ever,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod 17.14.16.</note> whom he had <hi>devoted</hi> to <hi>ruine</hi> and <hi>extirpation;</hi> We cannot hope to proſper and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail upon other Terms then <hi>Joſuah</hi> did. And truly you are too unkind, if while your Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-men
<pb n="XXXII" facs="tcp:62993:17"/>
               <hi>fight</hi> for you, you will not Pray for them; While they patiently endure <hi>Toil, Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Wounds,</hi> nay, <hi>loſe</hi> their <hi>Lives,</hi> you will not <hi>amend</hi> yours, will not do ſo delightful, ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable a thing, as to <hi>love</hi> and <hi>ſerve God,</hi> both for <hi>their ſakes</hi> and <hi>your own,</hi> to procure <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>ſafety</hi> in this <hi>World;</hi> and eternal <hi>Happineſs</hi> in that to come. Which God grant us all for the merits of Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:62993:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
